oh
[Music]
w
hello welcome back to the ask show I
hope you're all doing fantastic good
evening good day to everybody wherever
you are in the
world and today as you know I'm going to
take questions that you have asked in
the comments lots of interesting
questions have come in so I'm going to
take those very briefly let me see who
all is there on the live chat I can see
shaa Dr Sur dager
amay hello vishak n PR Paul from Kolkata
hello GSR cost J loes M WV 13113 Karan
nalat pamel nandi shiram Mund Gish KB
gav Krish SI Isabella giridhar strangely
proton xmus Yus zus endan Mech ech Hy
Sharma Surendra Gupta majar GI political
dub jho shamik Ray Rahul dun
giridhar uh ranvir
Rina shivendu sansi W Kumar
Sharma pan but Barat that is bat Jay
guman feminist sler Tanish Kumar van
again aishik kotal threat Tripper jitu
chetri saaj rakshit Mishra Kunal nagari
Akash ba mlav cost
jwall uh space KGB agent Martin Nath
anol Kumar Manisha MTI gorov sushil Pak
wisan Karan nwat shagun Chopra basant
007 udip DEA Krish s and everybody else
Priyanka Jalia ainash Sunil Kumar
giridhar an
mital and everyone else okay so what
questions do we have lots of questions
so let us go ahead with the questions I
can even see Joseph Stalin here who is
greeting us from the USSR
greetings great
leader okay let's take the questions
what questions do we
have okay the first question is by ARA
ARA Indra one one this is the first time
asking a question after almost two years
thank you so much thank you so much as a
Bengali I was paying much attention to
the current situation in East Pakistan
some of the high ranking military
personnel are relatives of shik
and she did some good economic growth
there very good growth yes after the
situation cools down this situation
concerning the coup maybe in five or six
years can we see shik Hina again
contesting there as a PM candidate and
maybe winning what's your opinion about
silently taking jitong region in India
by slowly cutting it off from Mainland
East Pakistan as it's a Hindu majority
area right that's the question uh so how
do I see things going I think it's very
early days is in the current regime in
in East Pakistan the current military
regime uh Muhammad yunus is this puppet
prime minister who has been installed by
the Americans but it's a military
government the coup happened when did
the coup happen the coup did not happen
when the students were protesting on the
streets the coup happened when the
Bangladesh Army Military gave shika 45
minutes to leave the country that's the
coup the military executed the coup so
it's a military government that you have
in in power in East Pakistan just like
in West Pakistan
so it's very early days right now they
still getting things in order they are
still you know putting up appearances
and so on and of course some of like you
said some of the uh military personnel
were are relatives of sh Kina well
that's how it goes when it comes to
money and power even family sometimes
doesn't matter as we can see in East
Pakistan uh so maybe in five or six
years do we see shik Hina again
contesting I mean returning to East
Pakistan and contesting as a PM
candidate maybe winning
I think that's a far-fetched
scenario uh I think she probably won't
return there to East Pakistan she's
currently in India and she'll stay in
India because that's the safe place
where she's safe where she is safe uh
the West doesn't want to give her Refuge
there because they would like her well
well she
was anti-west I am sure the West would
have attempted to buy her off as well
the same way that they were able to to
buy off the the the Bangladesh military
so I'm sure they attempted they must
have attempted to buy off shik and she
she rejected she would have rejected
those offers so she won't get any uh
Safe Haven in the west so I don't see
Shina returning to Bangladesh politics
East Pakistan politics probably won't
happen and that's what she has said
through one of her through through her
son I believe so I think it's highly
unlikely I would not say it's impossible
that she may return and contest
elections I think it's highly unlikely
that shik will return to East Pakistan
and be a p PM candidate in even win less
likely very unlikely now what about the
chagang region for that we have to look
at the map where's the map here's the
map the question is should India
silently take the Chittagong region into
India incorporate it into India by
cutting out by slowly cutting it off
from Mainland East Pakistan it's a Hindu
majority area and so on
so the region we're talking about is the
Chittagong Hill tract region so as you
can see we have the city of chattogram
or chagang over here and it it's a it's
uh a region that neighbors uh Burma and
various parts of Far Eastern India
including mizoram and tripura and as you
can see there's a chicken's neck here as
well if you look at this you will see
that uh it's about 25 28 km wide that's
that's the small sliver of land that
connects the chagang region to the rest
of East
Pakistan so it's it's extremely feasible
extremely easy actually for a military
operation to cut off this region from
the rest of East Pakistan so militarily
it's definitely very feasible it's no
big deal so that's the Bangladesh
Bangladeshi chicken neck which is
similar to the Indian chicken neck over
here the the Siliguri Corridor which is
about 22 23 kilm
wide strategically important region
similarly the same goes for chattagram
chagang that region and historically
that's uh Hindu Hindu and Buddhist
majority region I simply don't
understand why it was made part of East
Pakistan so the question is can India
quietly silently gradually take this
incorporate this region Chittagong Hill
tracks into India I think such a thing
can't be done silently or quietly the
moment make a move the bangladeshis I
mean the East pakistanis will will how
in protest
obviously they may even attempt some
kind of military operation which will
not go into the thing is it's very easy
to take if India wants to take it
but but we to understand that this new
nation or this this revamped Nation this
newly minted American client state has
the umbrella of us protection over it if
India does such a move the Americans
will claim that India is behaving just
like
like they say Russia and Ukraine and
they're going to impose sanctions on
India they want India to make a bad move
they want India to make a mistake I
don't think it's it makes sense for
India to do that right now to make a
move on chatram on the chagang hill
tracks region not right now right now
there are bigger problems a foot in the
region and that's something that India
needs to look at more proactively
compared to taking Chittagong which
eventually will happen but not as of
this this moment in time right now there
are bigger problems and bigger issues
that India has to deal with in this
region and that's I guarantee you what
India is focusing on right
now next question is by sayani Mei MD
okay Muhammad yunus the the puppet prime
minister of East Pakistan he recently
said in an interview that he wants to
revitalize SAR Sark has already been
replaced by bimc which is more
meaningful uh then why does he want to
revive
SAR so Muhammad unus wants to revitalize
and revive SAR first of all Muhammad
inos is a nobody he is a nobody he is
simply a puppet who is uh who has been
placed as the face of the military
regime so as to give the military regime
a little bit of
respectability and as we know he is
deeply associated with the US with the
US establishment and he's there he's
their
guy but politically he's a
nobody uh so when a nobody a puppet says
that he wants to do this or do that he's
essentially uh it's essentially the
words of his Masters that are that are
coming out of his mouth right so what is
SAR Sark is is now defunct it's obsolete
India has completely sidelined Sark Sark
there is no activity on the Sark front
Sark is the South Asian Association for
regional cooperation bimc is Bay of
Bengal something or the other it's it's
it's an organization a multilateral
organization uh devoted to economic
cooperation and other cooperation
between Bangladesh
India uh Myanmar Thailand Etc this
geographical area so one can say to some
extent it's an alternative to Sark on
the Eastern front for
India um so if Muhammad yunus is saying
that he wants to revitalize
Sark the question we to ask us is why
has Sark been
devitalized right if he wants to revive
Sark why has it been deived is question
we to ask ourselves and who has done it
we have done it India the Narendra Modi
government Mr Modi
himself has gone ahead and made SAR
dysfunctional uh s doesn't exist except
on paper anymore right why have we done
this because Sark gets a sark works very
fine except for one big problem Pakistan
wherever Pakistan exists there are
problems so we just don't want to be uh
running an
organization in which Pakistan is a
member we just don't want it we want to
completely sideline and marginalize
Pakistan and anything that comes with
Pakistan so Sark includes Pakistan so we
have shut down Sark essentially so if
Muhammad yunus the puppet prime minister
of East Pakistan wants to revitalize AR
it means that he wants to bring Pakistan
back into the picture because Pakistan
is the other big wasal state of the US
in the region the US now has two wasal
states east Pakistan and West Pakistan
West Pakistan is the well the the one
that the Sharif one of the Sharif
Brothers is is currently the puppet
prime minister of so the two wasal will
now synergize and they will try to
create mischief and problems for India
in a variety of ways whatever is
possible for them that's what Muhammad
unus is trying to do he is he's echoing
the words he's
essentially his Masters are speaking
through him they want Sark back in the
equation they want more problems for
India and Muhammad is a nobody let him
say whatever he wants he can go ahead
and and start Sark again if he wants but
without India's participation sh Sark
doesn't exist so and nobody else will go
along with that so that's the deal
they're just trying to create mischief
and problems for India that is the
entire purpose of Muhammad unus
existence okay pramuk D says will the
United States impose sanctions on India
if our government starts deporting
illegal Bangladeshi infiltrators and
Tushar kalburgi says how will the US
react if the government of Barat starts
to deport all the illegal Bangladeshi
infiltrators into present day East
Pakistan
uh the illegal okay the first the first
question is the first first point is
that we have to recognize the fact that
there's a there's a gigantic number of
East Pakistani Bangladeshi infiltrators
who are currently who currently exist in
India I think around 2014 the government
had said that there are about 50 million
bangladeshis in India five CR that's in
2014 and since then a lot of water has
flown under the bridge so if I were to
give a very rough guesstimate I would
say the number must have doubled by now
okay maybe a 100 million 10 CR illegal
East Pakistani infiltrat in infiltrators
in India who currently would be residing
in India they have this entire industry
which which you know gives them
placements in various parts of India
integrates them with various other
Bangladeshi infiltrators who already
reside in India gives them documentation
Adar cards whatnot so that industry is
entirely in place in Barat and they are
able to send Bangladeshi infiltrators
rohinga infiltrators to the far and wide
areas of India including in Jammu and
Kashmir we know
that now I would imagine that one of the
reasons why the government of India did
not take any action about this is that
shika was in power and sending rounding
these people up and deporting them to
Bangladesh would would to a large extent
the Bangladeshi economy we
didn't want that to happen but now that
Bangladesh no longer exists it's East
Pakistan it's it's a hostile Nation
maybe it makes sense to send back these
Bangladeshi East Pakistani infiltrators
that would be a long drawn out process
100 million is no small number it's a
gigantic number is bigger than most
countries bigger than the population of
most countries but let's say India does
that starts the process in Assam or
wherever and starts sending 2,000 back
every day rough hypothetically okay as
as an example what will happen well
first of all the entire ecosystem within
India the anti-india ecosystem that
exists in within India at various levels
in various institutions infiltrated
everywhere they will start a hu hu cry
about this a huge hu cry about this the
Indian media what whichever is bought
over by the anti-india elements they
will start a big human cry and that will
be the Quee for the global media to
start howling in protest and they'll say
that India is uh without reason uh
without giving a fair trial or whatever
uh India is indulging in human rights
abuses and India India is indulging in
in selective targeting on the basis of
religion and what not they're going to
make all these
stories is going to and they will
definitely I guarantee you they'll
succeed in tarnishing the the reputation
and name of India it's going to be a
very successful campaign the entire
Western media world will ecosystem will
will jump on board on this so you will
have various uh German Publications like
DW and whatnot uh French Publications
will will be on board all the European
Publications will be on board about this
you know media
Outlets uh in in in the UK you will have
the guardian the BBC who will Who will
devote vast amounts of of of
journalistic real estate to this and
obviously the New York Times Washington
Post they will create this entire
narrative globally Australian media will
be will be on board and so on they will
come together and combine to create this
vast gigantic concerted
avalanch this narrative against India
that will be very bad for India's
reputation you travel abroad people will
look you look at you in a very bad way
that's what they'll do and that will be
just just be the start if India still
persists they will they may even impose
sanctions upon
India so that's the deal that's how
powerful the ecosystem is I think we are
saddled with these illegal infiltrators
for some time to for some time at least
and like I said right now is may not be
the time to deal with the illegal East
Pakistan is in India obviously it's a
huge threat for India it's a very
powerful asset the Americans have within
India if they want to unleash Mayhem
they can using the illegal East bang
East Pakistani infiltrators they can do
that so that's in a way it's a ticking
ticking Time Bomb but probably not one
you want to diffuse right now yeah uh
because we have bigger problems in the
region like I said in India's Far East
that is something India will have to
deal with on a more priority basis
probably in alignment with another with
maybe one or two other countries that
are kind of in alignment with us
perhaps okay Tech wise 360 says Putin
has said that NATO will be in direct
conflict with Russia if Ukraine uses the
Western Long Range missiles is the
situation that bad right now so what's
happened so since the uh special
military operation began in February
2022 uh the West the US and it's
various minions puppets have been
supplying Ukraine with arms ammunition
and so on including short range uh
things missiles whatever even long range
missiles with the caveat that uh Ukraine
will only use short range weapon systems
and artillery and and whatever uh across
the border with Russia and whatever
longrange missile systems the ukrainians
may have they will use it only within
ukra Ukrainian territory which in eyes
of Ukraine is currently occupied by
Russia that's been the deal now it looks
like the Americans will be okay with
giving Ukraine the goahead to use wrong
long range missile systems for
crossborder strikes into Russian
territory deep into Russian territory
and I believe that the missile system
that's uh being spoken about right now
is the Storm Shadow cruise
missile this depending on where you look
what source you look at this missile
system seems to have a range of between
250 km to 550 km depending where you
look what source you're looking at so
it's a reasonably I would call it a
medium range missile system but you can
say it's no longer tactical and short
range so you can call it a long range
missile system so using this missile
system the ukrainians could hit deep
into Russian territory let's take a look
at the map and let's see how far they
could uh go so so um we're talking about
Ukraine here so let's say so we know
that they are in control of
KV and let's see if you go to VOR Von
it's 250 260 kilom so they can
definitely hit vones how far is let's
say Moscow from Northern
Ukraine Moscow is about 545 kilomet so
it's at the the outer range of the Storm
Shadow missile cruise missile system so
using this cruise missile system or any
other cruise missile SYM maybe a longer
range one they could hit Moscow and it
deep into Russian territory so that's a
whole different Paradigm we're looking
at that's a whole different kind of
warfare we're looking at thus thus far
the ukrainians they have not been
allowed by NATO by the west by the
Americans to do this now it looks like
they will get the goahead to do that but
here's the
deal these Weapons Systems missile
systems they have to be Long Range
Systems you have to input
coordinates into them you have to input
a f flight path into these missile
systems so that they know where to fly
and what to
hit
and only NATO technicians are allowed to
do this so essentially you will have a
missile system a missile that's going to
be fired from Ukrainian territory into
Russia and a NATO technician who will
either be American or european Western
European will go and input the
coordinates of the Target and the flight
into the
missile so now you have direct NATO
involvement do you understand the
difference until now it was the short
Range Systems the Ukrainian Army was
using now the the the order to fire may
be given by a Ukrainian Soldier General
whatever the the button will be pressed
but the inputs will be uh fed into the
system by NATO technici at least that is
what Putin
says so now if this happens it's going
to be a whole different kind of warfare
a whole different level of warfare and
Vladimir Putin has spoken about this and
he has said that if NATO allows the
ukrainians to use long range missiles
against Russia he's going to consider it
to that he's going to consider this to
mean that Russia that NATO is now
directly at war with Russia there is no
proxy in between anymore the proxy was
Ukraine now it's NATO versus Russia
straight
away and he considers that to be a whole
different kind of warfare a whole
different escalation he and he says that
Russia will respond
appropriately so we we are staring at a
significant level of escalation here now
how would Russia respond Russia has all
different kinds of ways of responding a
variety of ways in which they could
respond this means that they will no
longer
Target
uh targets they will no
longer you know hit out at Targets
merely within Ukraine they will now be
free to hit out at Targets in and Target
locations that are within NATO Nations
or assets that belong to Nato Nations
one example is they could take out
a potentially a British aircraft carrier
using one of their Hypersonic missiles
perhaps the the ciron missile or
whatever they could do that as a
warning um so we're looking at
significant escalation if the West
allows the ukrainians to use longrange
missile systems against
Russia uh now what what should we make
of this the the Western commentary that
comes out from the the higher echelons
of of the US military in NATO is that
Putin is
bluffing and if if Russia's red lights
existed they have been crossed long
ago that's the kind of commentary that's
coming out of the west of NATO of the Us
Now understand one thing Putin never
Bluffs from the time when he was in
charge of a single city until where he
has reached now he has never bluffed he
he makes it a point to remind people to
remind the world that he has never
bluffed his words have meaning his his
words carry weight when he says
something he means it and he does
it and the US would like us to believe
that no no you know it's all Bluff and
there are no red lines and we have
already crossed the red lines and the
Russians did nothing
so we are looking at two very different
versions of what's happening in the
world two very different
narratives and one of these is correct
one of these is
false so I I hope that this escalation
doesn't happen I hope the Americans
don't give the ukrainians to go ahead to
use these long range weapons because I
in my estimation the Russians will will
respond appropriately like they say what
is appropriate there they're going to
decide what appropriate is but it's not
going to be fun it's going to be a big
escalation and
then then the US will reuse that as a PR
as the pretext to escalate further and
you see what's happening you going up
very rapidly up the chain of es
escalation and what's up there at the
top World Annihilation nuclear exchange
which is the end of the world we never
want to even consider that so who is
escalating right now the Americans are
escalating they should step back
they should calm things down they should
deescalate but no they're trying to
escalate
further so that's where we are very
dangerous days we are living through
right now very dangerous
days uh so that's the deal with uh with
that now what's the next
question Nicholas
luminato says talk about the Sri Lankan
elections and
Kish Kish okay says can you talk about
the Sri Lankan elections which candidate
will be the best for
India so yes Sri Lanka's elections Sri
Lanka's election is coming up the
presidential election so let's recap
what's happened of late in Sri Lanka
so Sri
Lanka underwent a sovereign debt default
in 2022 and as a consequence of that the
in the entire Financial economic crisis
that ensued gotabaya Raja Paka was outed
as the President of Sri Lanka sometime
in 22 I think July
2022 and since then we've had ranil
vikas sing who's been the president
there was a brief interum in between but
ranil vikam sing is the current
incumbent president now the Sri Lankan
Election Commission has said that the
upcoming presidential election will
happen on the 21st of September this
year so today is what today is the 15th
of September so less than a week to go
for the Sri Lankan presidential election
now there's a number of candidates and
parties who are in the frey in the
presidential election we have the
incumbent current president ranel Vikram
sing Who strangely enough is running as
an independent candidate I'll not go
into the reasons why so he's running as
an independent candidate for president
then there is the uh opposition leader
sjit PR ASA who's the son of the Pres of
the former president R sing ra Rana sing
premadasa so so sjit premadasa is the
opposition leader he is running for
president then you have anura Kumar
danay who is the leader of the Nationals
people's of the national people's
movement so he's he's the third guy his
party has historically and of late been
rather critical of India's involvement
in Sri Lanka they have been suspicious
of the Chinese involvement in Sri Lanka
as well but danay recently visited India
a few months ago the first quarter of
this
year so it looks like U he may be or his
party may be more favorably inclined
towards India off late then namal rajap
Paka the son of the former prime
minister former president mahinda rajap
Paka is also standing for election and
so on so that is the deal right now now
what's happened in Sri Lanka is that Sri
Lanka has slipped into poverty in the
past four five years uh in 2019 about
11% of Sri Lankans were living under the
poverty line right now it's almost 25%
disaster the economy has backslid very
badly and there are all kinds of issues
in Sri Lanka so what are the issues that
the election presidential election will
be fought on first of all reduction in
corruption there's apparently tremendous
corruption in Sri Lanka reduction of the
of the tax burden on middle class
working citizens well sounds similar to
India but yeah apparently they taxed
heavily and they would like the tax
burden to be reduced then the need to
ensure the stability of prices of of
Essentials in Sri Lanka uh the need to
keep inflation steady in Sri Lanka and
then there are other issues like
U uh accountability for the Electoral
for the economic bankruptcy Sri Lanka
went bankrupt it defaulted on its
Sovereign date and so on in 20 2022 so
who's going to be accountable for this
and what action is going to be taken
about that that's another issue
constitutional reforms economic reforms
then you have this terrorist attack 2019
Easter Sunday attack bombing attack on
on church and all that so what so people
want legal action to be to be uh taken
um
speedily against the perpetrators of the
terrorists who were behind this attack
and there are all kinds of delays
apparently procedural delays there's
lack of transparency there is allegedly
political interference in the matter all
that
so these are some of the issues that
there is the Chinese investment inflows
and debt that Sri Lanka owes to China
many of these projects the Chinese
undertook are non-performing there is no
return on the investment Ham Port is an
example the matala rajap Paka
international airport near Hamad the
Columbo Lotus tower all of these
projects have sent Sri Lanka into a debt
trap and they owe this lots of money to
China
and when and all of these things put
together sent Sri Lanka into the
financial crisis bankruptcy and India
was the first country to help Sri Lanka
India provided an extended Lifeline of
more than4 billion dollar India also
provided a$1 billion credit line to Sri
Lanka to help the country uh overcome
the immediate crisis so India has been
the first responder India has been doing
that and uh so that's the background
that's that's what's happened in brief
so you have three four candidates the
current uh president is probably the
front runner and sjit prasa also is
is is one of the major candidates the
Sak Etc so who's going to be good for
India is the question I think whoever is
willing to cooperate with India perhaps
theay he seems to be inclin towards
India R vikr sing is probably one can
regard as a western Pro West kind of
leader an IMF guy
perhaps
Viking but whoever is willing to work
with
India um and and strengthen India Sri
Lanka cooperation and so on is going to
be good for India right now I'm not sure
if any of these candidates has what it
takes to solve all the problems but the
country needs to go forward so that's
the deal right now election in less than
a week's time I am not by any means an
expert on Sri Lankan politics but this
is what I can give this is the kind of
overview I can offer you and let's see
uh what happens in six days time in Sri
Lanka okay vami krishnam 5077 says I
recently read that International
election observers have arrived in Sri
Lanka to monitor the presidential
elections why do they get involved in a
country's internal election process well
I assure you that you will not have
international election Observers in an
election in let's say Italy or France or
Norway or Den Denmark you won't have uh
International election observers in
elections in Canada in New Zealand in
Australia in the UK in the US so what's
the deal so these so-called
International election observers are
generally individuals from certain
Western countries who come to observe
the electoral process in a more backward
country Sri Lanka is is an Eastern
country brown people
right brown people they must be very
backward so their electoral process has
to be observed and monitored so that the
world can know whether it's been a fair
and transparent election or
not and similarly when there are
elections in India these election inter
these International election observers
descend upon India like a horde of
vultures and the same happens in various
other Eastern
Nations so I would say so so it's just
this superiority complex that we have
Superior to you and most likely your
electoral process is flawed not up to
the mark not up to our standards we in
the US have Flawless elections see 2020
what happened how Flawless it was H what
a joke so I think when the upcoming
president presidential election happens
in the US probably November or whenever
it is this year I think India should
send a team of let's say 2,000 or
3,000 election observers to observe the
election and monitor the progress of the
election and
ensure that the election is held as per
International standards and there is no
rigging and no scary I think India
should do that India should send
observers a team of maybe 2 or 3,000
observers I would urge the government of
India to do this to ensure that the
world the the Civilized world knows that
there there is hopefully free and fair
election elections happening in the US
transparently and if and if there is any
issue then it should be brought to
light
okay okay sair Kazi says I was
calculating the US power while while
setting aside emotions propaganda
Chinese hype and concerns about us
then I realize that the true strength of
the US lies in its strong fundamentals
including a robust business environment
and advanced education system leading
companies a for and a formidable defense
industry Additionally the US exerts
significant Global influence through
financial control such as the US dollar
which is the world's Reserve currency
International institutions like the wh
the UN and the World Bank and and the
vast network of 750 plus military bases
which are extra territorial in nature in
comparison Russia China and India are
nowhere near the US what's your take on
this uh so what you say makes
uh sense the question is uh what are the
components that that go into
constructing the score calculating the
score for a nation's power when we
talking about power we're talking about
hard power otherwise you you will have
all kinds of uh random not random random
but all kinds of subjective factors that
you will have to include so what are the
main components of a nation's hard power
score first of all the land area that's
available to a nation because that gives
you an indication of how much resources
the nation has access to first of all
land area second population a large
population gives you more manpower which
is good for you population is is a
factor uh then you have your national
GDP annual GDP what's your annual GDP is
very important then your defense
expenditure year your military budget
for for annually the latest one that's
what goes into it and then there are
factors like uh the number of nuclear
weapons you have in case you have any
that is a significant factor and also
your power projection ability how much
of the global area can you cover in
terms of power projection what
percentage of the global area let's say
in terms of power projection then you
consider risk risk factors like um uh
like energy
self-sufficiency uh sovereignty how
Sovereign the nation is and so on so
that's these are the ingredients that go
into the into the into making the soup
okay that's the national that's a
nation's hard power score now strong
fundamentals obviously matter robust
business environment but how do you how
do you uh assign a score to a
nation's business environment and its
robustness it's kind of subjective
subjective you really can't then how do
you assign a score out of 10 let's say
to a nation's education system you can
do it subjectively and you may be able
to do a good job of it but you really
can't do it precisely and accurately now
the quality of your companies once again
it's kind of subjective defense industry
you can put a score on that based on the
annual defense expenditure so many of
these things are are to large extent
subjective and if you ask five different
experts or researchers they will
probably give you five different answers
for the scores of these things like the
quality of the education system the
robustness of the business environment
and so so on so forth which is why you
typically don't uh include those factors
those subjective factors in constructing
uh a nation's hard power score the only
factors you can reliably use to
construct a hard power score calculate a
hard power score
are publicly available
numbers that no one can dispute that's
how you do it that way nobody can
dispute your calculations or at least uh
the reasoning behind your calculations
the the equation the formula that you
use is up to you and some portion of
that has to be classified hopefully but
that's how you do it uh but overall
you're right that uh the US is way way
way ahead of all other nations
the one nation that comes kind of close
to the us it's about half of the US
slightly more than the half the US's
hard power score is
Russia and then you have China which is
nowhere close to Russia and then you
have India which is about three and a
half times smaller than China in terms
of hard hard power score so that's the
way the the world is currently the the
uh the power equations are currently
aligned the world right now so I to a
large extent agree with you I wish there
was a a reliable way of unambiguously
assigning a score toward a Nations
business environment's robustness to its
education system and so on but you
really can't which is
why I don't include those factors in
calculating a nation's hard par score
but the factors that I did mention I do
include
those okay har Agarwal asks a pretty
long question but interesting let's see
the global times wrote an article
criticizing Dr s s janker India's
foreign minister but deleted the English
version just a few years later China
recently extradited a khalistani
terrorist and the Maldives have started
Maldives which is the Chinese wasal has
started engaging with India again even
after pro-china government yes what's
cooking between the two Nations India
and China and editing this later on 13
September because of a few developments
uh Mr doal India's national security
adviser met with China's for Minister Mr
Wang Y and both of them issued a joint
statement for resolving the ladak
standoff urgently urgently being the
operative word here the US has started
to counter this by sanctioning Chinese
companies for the involvement in the
temporary Nations ballistic missile
program and the Americans are offering
their 50-year-old F-16 Jets to India
what's your thoughts on this is r i see
really a possibility because of threats
from Uncle
Sam lots happening
so you've done a good job of outlining
what's happening the global times has
historically been so what is the global
times it's a Chinese
publication they are active on Twitter
and they have their own website and
Twitter generally tweets excerpts of
what they or or or abstracts of what the
the articles are and they link to the
articles on the global times website and
it's a Chinese government mouthpiece
just like the BBC is a British
government mouthpiece in the New York
Times Washington Post Etc are American
government mouthpieces so every nation
typically has one India doesn't have it
of course India is is a is is okay let's
not go into that that matter so the
global times is one of the Chinese
government's mouthpieces Publications
right and historically they've had a
rather strident anti-india tone the
global times and their Publications okay
so recently this this article came out
criticizing India's foreign minister Dr
J Shankar and a few hours later the
article vanished it was pulled out it
was pulled it was deleted from the
Twitter account and from the website
itself so that's interesting what why
did
they delete an article that's critical
of the Indian foreign minister
interesting the Chinese recently exited
a khalistani terrorist to India that's
incredible that's unheard of China
cooperating with India in Terr in
matters of terrorism unheard of first in
history I'm sure what's going on in
Maldives has a pro government their
their Prime their leader muu Mr muuu has
had this anti-india campaign India out
campaign he's known to be a Chinese a
pro-chinese uh politician so there's a
pro-chinese government in the Maldives
and they after muu Mr muu came to power
he uh ordered the uh eviction of Indian
Armed Forces Personnel a small number
that we had and and
and the withdrawal of Indian companies
and so so much more so
and and yet now the Maldives is
cooperative with India it's engaging
with India it's awarding projects to
Indian companies all of a sudden this W
to fast has happened this complete
U-turn has happened so what's going on
is the question what's going on between
India and China and uh India's NSA Mr
doal met with the Chinese foreign
minister wangi who's a very high rank
ranking leader uh very high rank ranking
official they issued a joint state
there is talk of resolving the ladak
standoff urgently it started because of
Chinese actions entirely Chinese created
crisis obviously we know that now about
75% of it seems to have seen complete
disengagement about 25% is left but
hopefully that also gets disengaged so
you will have return to relative
normaly uh on the India Tibet Border in
ladak in the ladak
region something is a foot between India
and China clearly and the Americans now
have sanctioned some Chinese companies
for their involvement in Pakistani
ballistic missile program it's so funny
the Americans have propped up Pakistan
forever but they're sanctioning Chinese
companies for their involvement in the
ballistic missile program and the
Americans are offering F-16 fighter
planes to India India should not take
those those are well look the
F-16 program is about 50 years old it
doesn't mean the fighters they are
offering to India were constructed years
ago there'll be new new uh Jets
constructed uh a new with with
reasonably good technology uh more
modern Technologies Etc but you don't
want to be part of the to have us
Weaponry because it gives if it gives
them immense control over your military
as the Australians discovered with the
f60 uh with the
f-15s which refused to lock onto targets
the Australians wanted them to lock onto
you don't want to be saddled with a
bunch of crippled aircraft you don't
want that so uh so obviously India if
India has any sense will will will pass
on the offer of f16s so the Americans
clearly are sensing that something is
cooking between India and China and
they're trying to well make some moves
accordingly so that's the deal so the
final question that heril is asking is
is r i really a possibility because of
threats from Uncle Sam so r i is a
coalition of Russia India China that's
what Ric is now Russia and India are on
excellent terms no qu no no concerns
there there's a significant amount
amount of convergence in and the
convergence when it comes to the
national interests of Russia as well as
India Russia and
China get along reasonably fine they
have this cooperation that's been going
on for quite some time uh a modu sendi
of sorts they
have and then there's India and China
India and China share a long
undemarcated border because the Chinese
have steadfastly refused to demarcate
the border and that's the Crux of the
issue and the Chinese claim more Indian
Territory which is the root cause of all
the hostility and the Bad Blood between
between the two
Nations and they have this practice of
Sala slicing attempting to salami SLI
into IND Indian Territory cross over the
perceived line of actual control and so
on so forth Chinese aggression that's
why there is this issue between India
and
China question is can r i happen first
of all why should r i happen why should
India China Russia come together the
answer is very simple all three are
being targeted by the US Russia has is
is facing the brunt of the whole gamut
of us sanctions right now China is
involved in a trade war with the US the
Americans are China various kinds of
Technology the Chinese are retaliating
in in kind when it comes to rare earth
metals and whatnot um Chinese want
Taiwan the Americans are propping up
Taiwan and so much more right so China
is facing the heat from the US Russia is
definitely facing the heat from the US
and when it comes to India the Americans
are trying to uh create all kinds of
problems with with Vis A India they've
affected a regime change in East
Pakistan they are they are in the
process of attempting to create an
artificial cookie Nation Christian
Nation cookie land in India's Far East
out of out of Manipur mizoram and Burma
and and parts of Bangladesh parts of all
these territories that's extremely
hostile action the Americans are are
indulging in subnational diplomacy and
trying to destabilize India through that
so much more and they have so many
fronts open they they are funding
industrial scale Christian conversions
in various parts of India so much more
the Americans are doing India China
Russia all three are facing the heat
from the US when it comes to India the
Americans see India as a future
long-term threat if India is allowed to
grow so the growth must stop so India
needs to be destabilized in a variety of
ways that's what they're working on
right now it's very quite it's quite
evident it's quite open it's quite
blatant
actually so all three big
Nations Russia India China the three
Eastern nations are facing the heat
makes sense to come
together and the regim change in in
Bangladesh in East Pakistan has affected
China definitely China had their own
thing going on over there over the
regime change in in Pakistan West
Pakistan which happened in 22 turned a
Chinese wasal into us wasal that's a big
loss for China so they lost East
Pakistan as well as West Pakistan West
Pak East Pakistan was never really
theirs but they were they had reasonably
okay relationship with with SH A's
government then there's a Civil War in
Burma which
well which essentially can be seen as a
as as as a proxy tussle between the US
and China so the existing burmes
government the Legacy burmes government
has historically been Pro China and the
Americans have made big inroads there
through the cookie terrorist and
whatnot so that's a big setback for
China Mak so that's the situation so it
makes
sense for RC to
happen the three East
Powers
cooperate and pull their resources to
some extent together and that will allow
them enable them to withstand the
Western pressure
better that's the kind of thing if it
happens it's it's in the very very early
stages if it is going to ever
happen first of all the question is how
can India ever trust China after all all
the backstabbing and all the all
everything China has done since the
1950s
China simply can't be trusted so then
how can R happen
well if the Chinese want India's trust
they will have to demonstrate that they
are worthy of trust and India will have
to take it on a step by step Case by
case day byday basis the Crux of the
matter is the border which the Chinese
have refused to
demarcate the first step is
disengagement which is happening very
surprising but it's happening next I
think the border uh demarcation will
take time even if it's done urgently may
take months maybe take take a few years
perhaps two three years but as a
confidence building measure India and
China could do a pilot project somewhere
in the neighborhood let's say and and
kind of defang some snakes so that's
something we could do
perhaps so that's all I'll say about
that neighborhood common neighborhood
India China maybe let's
see okay rates Pia says can a NATO
member turkey join bricks in the past we
have seen France we have SE that France
also showed a desire to become a member
of bricks and they wanted to take part
in the bricks Summit last year how would
the US look at such a development so
turkey is the is kind of the Joker in
the pack so to say when it comes to the
NATO Nations the Turks have their own
Ambitions and their own agenda tur let's
take a look at where turkey is but
turkey is very important for NATO why is
turkey so important for NATO it's
because it it commands a strategic
position in uh at the crossroads of what
is regarded as Asia and
Europe so turkey uh is in possession
of the straight of
Bosphorus this is
a
um so the Turkish Straits is the prized
possession that turkey uh
owns the straight that exists between
the black Black Sea and the Sea of
marara which goes through
Istanbul so that's the straight of Boss
forus that's an incredibly important
water weave
and then you have the straight of the
dardel where lots of action happened in
in World War I uh 1915 this is another
incredibly important uh geographical
choke point so turkey controls two vital
choke points between the Black Sea and
the Mediterranean Sea and any warship
that passes through these traits has to
has to display itself it has to show
itself it cannot do it cannot pass
through through unseen undetected
according to the treaties that have been
signed essentially it's about Russia
because the Black Sea region is
dominated by Russia you have Crimea you
have the Ukraine region you have uh
parts of Russia and Russian dominated
territories and you have the Black Sea
Fleet the Russian Black Sea Fleet which
is based in sevastopol and the other re
parts of the region us to be Odessa as
well during the USSR days now it's
mainly sasta
Paul Sim fop and so
so any Russian warship that need that
wants to Transit from the Black Sea to
the Mediterranean has to pass through
the straight of Bosphorus and the
straight of the Dells that is why turkey
is so important for
NATO and turkey has been rent
seeking it based on its geographical
location for the longest time and
extracting favors from the west and
that's why the US likes to keep turkey
in good humor and you know that's why
turkey gets a little more leave than
other nations
in NATO now turkey has its own Imperial
Ambitions it used to be the Ottoman
Empire obviously they will want to
revive the Empire someday in the future
and Mr erdogan the current Sultan I mean
the current current leader of turkey has
those oversized or Neo otoman Ambitions
they are active in parts of Syria they
they've been active in parts of Iraq as
well Turkish soldiers right um it is
alleged that they had something to do
with Isis as well dases whatever going
to call it names don't matter the the
organization actually matters and they
are also involved in North Africa the
Turks so they have these oversized
geopolitical Ambitions and they have
this LoveHate pimes relationship with
Russia which goes back to the ottoman
days
okay um and the Turks have acquired the
Russian
S400 system because of which they were
frozen out of the F35 program by the
Americans and so on and so forth A lot
has gone down
in this region so now coming back to
Bricks once we understand the
geographical aspect of it why turkey is
important because of The Straits the the
waterways it controls uh so turkey on
the one hand has its own agenda which is
separate and distinct from that of
NATO they would like to have reasonably
good relationship with Russia which is
something that NATO with NATO and the
Americans won't want but it's there
erdogan and Putin have a reasonably
decent working
relationship so now what about bricks
the Turks seem to have indicated that
they want to be a member of
bricks well can you be on two camps
simult in two two opposing camps
simultaneously you really can't right
the French tried that they M Mak wanted
France to become a member of bricks and
participate in the brick Summit
obviously that was vetoed that was
rejected uh by whatever mechanism bricks
has and now turkey so France is one of
the core members of NATO long standing
me member of NATO so is turkey so now
that France obviously was rejected now
turkey is trying this so why would
turkey do this is it that the Americans
have told turkey to try and infiltrate
NATO just like they may have told France
to do
that so is it that turkey is trying to
be a spy Within bricks on behalf of NATO
or is it that turkey actually wants to
be a part of NATO I think there's a bit
of both it's a superposition of both uh
possibilities to some extent turkey may
act as a spy if it gets into into into
bricks spy on behalf of NATO also turkey
may actually want to be part of NATO and
be on the because it's an Eastern nation
anyway and it would like to gain some
benefits from whatever benefits bricks
has to offer so it's I think it's it's
it's kind of both so what's going to
happen will turkey be allowed into into
breaks I think not because if you're a
member of NATO you essentially from the
perspective of of Russia and China at
least you were the enemy right India is
is also kind of on both Sid we are not
India is not a member of NATO or member
of anything India is a member of the
Quad which is not a military Alliance so
India is not a treaty member of any
anti-russia or anti-china organization
the the quad can be portrayed to be kind
of
anti-china but uh it it doesn't have any
such thing in the chter and all that so
that's where you
are so how should how will the US look
at this development the US probably to
some extent may be behind this they may
have told the Turks try and get into
bricks they may be behind this and if
they're not they would be very concerned
but I think they may perhaps be behind
such a move
okay Rishi Gupta 09 says why has the
Modi government failed to protect
Manipur he has row IB ni full majority
in Parliament still it's burning for the
past one year and twinkle P says that uh
he won't answer this question ELO okay
and Pur purushotam jwani says what do
you
think could be the reason for the
government not taking completely control
of Manipur even after the military has
entered Manipur for a long time since
since a long time now is the military
finding it hard to handle infiltrators
is Manipur becoming the next the new
Kashmir okay pretty uh complicated
matter first of all I am taking the
question now let's take a look at the
region the Far East of India Manipur
where it is okay
uh that that's the region okay I'll take
it off screen for some time the first
question
is uh why has the government of India
the Modi government not taken complete
control of Manipur so is that true is
the government not in complete control
of
Manipur probably it's true I think half
of Manipur is overun by Cookie
infiltrators and wherever the cookies
are I don't think the government of
India has complete control over those
regions uh it's it's a mess
and do one does
we does one blame Modi for this
well at the end of the day he's the
Prime Minister and the buck stops with
him so he has to be blamed yes but who's
actually messed up over here I think
there's multiple levels of failure first
of all what's happened thus
far uh intelligence failure for sure did
they not see this coming hundreds of
thousands of illegal inators Crossing
into India it's been happening for
decades I understand but a lot A lot has
happened apparently in the past past
decade or so also it's been continuing
because of the open borders now even if
they knew that this is happening fencing
that border will take years okay and
there was this agreement between India
and Burma before the Civil War broke
out so maybe it would have see it would
have seemed that these people who are
crossing over the Border will go back
because that's the general pattern of
movement but it did not happen and they
settled down in Manipur and more than
half of Manipur the southern part of
Manipur has been over run by the foreign
infiltrators and terrorists so there is
an intelligence failure for sure there's
also a failure on on the on the part of
the Whoever has been advising the Modi
government about the far east region
about the Manipur region because most
Central governments don't know much
about the far East of India Manipur
mizoram nagaland Etc they don't know
anything about this region very farflung
area and the people are hardly visible
so who cares kind of like that so you
need subject matter experts or in in
people who have apparently expertise in
the region so I wonder who the experts
were okay who have been advising the
Modi government about Manipur those
experts they have messed up royally okay
they essentially have led the government
up the wrong
tree and and there are other
organizations who are trying
to involve all stakeholders I I mean are
foreign infiltrator terrorists
stakeholders in India really I'll not
even name the organization but all that
is is is going on even
now uh so that's what's happened the
illegal infiltration has been happening
for decades many of these foreigners
were settled by successive Indian
governments in the 20th century also
continuing the policy of the British
settling foreigners on Indian soil what
kind of imbecilic policy is that but
that's what the successive Indian
governments did in in the 20th century
and we've had this open border policy
with Burma because Burma has
historically been a friendly nation
which it is but see what is it has
resulted in when the open border policy
was weaponized against
us now there is foreign involvement in
the region without a doubt so Burma the
burmes government has has histo
historically been kind of
pro-china but the US has got involved in
the past 20 years in a very major way
especially during the Barack Obama
regime um so let's not go into the whole
story of that but there is significant
American involvement in Burma Baptist
missionaries are very active there all
the cookies the cookies are a non burmes
tribe ethnic group they don't speak the
Burmese language they don't practice
burmes culture they don't respect burmes
Customs nothing they are foreign to
Burma also they've come in further east
into Burma a few centuries ago like two
three centuries ago probably from Yan in
China or thereabouts uh so this
understanding has to be
there in the experts who are advising
the government clearly they were
clueless these so-called
experts uh I'm not naming any particular
person there are some experts who are
genuinely respect okay not all but well
you get the
drift so there is that now what what
happens um so now what the
military look the
military first of all we have to
understand there have been paramilitary
forces in in the Far East of India in
Manipur for a very long time there is
some to some extent some involvement of
the actual Indian military which is the
Indian army which is not paramilitary
force paramilitary forces are police
forces the Assam rifles are a police
force they are paramilitary Force so is
the crpf now the Assam rifles are being
trans shifted out of Manipur for good
reason and that also the government
probably did not see
coming okay when it comes to the Assam
rifles what had to be done and what was
going on I'll not go into further
details but yeah the Assam rifles are it
looks like they're being moved out of
Manipur and the crpf is is being brought
in and the Indian military the actual
armed forces the military is also there
in certain numbers we'll not go into
those
numbers now how do we deal de with
foreign
infiltrators the moment you try and move
them out or whatever they have they have
essentially unlimited supplies of arms
and ammunition okay these these kooki
terrorists how where are they getting
them from from Burma but Burma is in
Civil War so where are those factions
finding fighting the Civil War getting
the arms and ammunition from the
government would probably get supplies
from China but what about others how
come incredibly sophisticated siga and
whatever arms and ammunition are
available to the terrorists how come
they have access to drones imagine drone
bombing on the capital city of an Indian
State that's what's
happening so it's a disastrous situation
no doubt uh the military Indian military
Indian armed forces are in place not
for well they are there for other
reasons um when it comes to the the the
terrorists the infiltrators they will
have to be dealt with by the
paramilitary forces in whatever way is
appropriate National interest must come
first obviously right and just because
somebody has is holding an AAR card or
whatever doesn't make them a citizen
that's what happens typically so it's
it's a very complicated situation I
should not even discuss it in in in
great depth but understand this this I
will say uh let's put it put the map
back on the screen and you will
understand why I refer to the map M the
solution to this problem remember
Kashmir remember the Pakistani terrorism
in Kashmir here's Kashmir where was the
solution where is the solution to the
terrorism that has happened in Kashmir
the solution is not in Kashmir the
solution is west of the Border in
Pakistan right that's where the root
caus is and that's where the solution
lies otherwise you're simply reacting to
what's happening on your territory
without addressing the problem the the
the root of the problem which is outside
your territory similarly when it comes
to
Manipur the solution is outside of
Manipur it's east of
Manipur and that's
where the problem will be solved
whenever it is
solved how long will it take it depends
on a m multitude of factors now here's
the
deal you have obviously spoken about
Prime Minister Modi the Modi government
has failed uh and so on which is true
thus
far and do you realize that this makes
Prime Minister Modi look very
weak it
does whenever Mr Modi says something on
Twitter tweets something people say what
about Manipur what about Manipur what
happened to the 56 in inch chest true
right that is a genuine question and
question that well the government is
keeping quiet on for whatever reason
right now now understand this this has
dented Mr Mod's image and he can't
afford this to
happen so solution will come rest
assured and when it comes when the
hammer
Falls it'll fall hard but there are
certain other factors that need to be
hammered out before the hammer falls on
the
terrorists and those factors are
currently being looked at right
now
what will happen or what should happen
is India needs to
uh
engage with another aligned nation in
this strangely aligned but
aligned and some kind of joint venture
will be done will have to be
done to resolve the Burma problem in
such a way that the actual root cause of
the terrorism Which is far far away from
the region can't do a thing about
it so what's the root cause of the
terrorism that's happening the cookies
are the symptom right they have been
empowered by somebody and and armed by
somebody that's the root
cause so um the the problem will have to
be solved in such a way that the root
cause is is is rendered important in
this region so it's going to have to be
a joint venture between India and
another aligned country and the action
will be outside of India India that's
how I see the solution being brought
about but Mr Modi knows that he can't
afford to be inactive on this front for
too long it's already been more than a
year the entire Mayhem started in in May
last year apparently out of nowhere the
government is completely caught unawares
big failure for sure but now the
solution has to be found the indigenous
people of a state who have been staying
there for 2,000 plus years are suffering
the terrorists are are riging bombs from
drones on the capital city of a state in
India and right now the government of
India looks very weak and
helpless and this can't
continue so the Indian
military does exist it is
there it it needs a certain kind of
go-ahead at a certain point in time and
I hope it happens sooner than later
because it's already very late
okay Bobby epen good to see you Bobby
epen uh Bobby says what do you think
about recent findings about the Shroud
of Turin the shroud of toino yes the
Shroud of Turin so what is the Shroud of
Turin let's go to Google and see image
of shoud of ttin shall we so let us go
to our friend Google blank
page and we will say
shoud of Turin
so this is reputed to be a
cloth a linen cloth that uh Bears the
image of Jesus Christ so U it is said
that this is the
cloth at least some claims have been
made that this is the original cloth in
which the body of Jesus Christ was
wrapped after his crucifixion and after
he was brought down from the cross and
that's what Left Behind the the these
these markings that uh
depict uh Jesus Christ with his wounds
uh the lacerations on his back from the
flogging he was given by the Roman
soldiers the the injuries on the head
from the crown of of of thorns and and
the Stigmata on the hands and feet from
uh the the injuries uh that were caused
by the nails of the Cross and so on so
that's what the Shroud of Turin is it
apparently surfaced sometime in the 12th
or 13th
century and and it was immediately
denounced by some members of the church
hiring members of the church as a
forgery but then it it was after some
time taken to be the genuine article it
was venerated and displayed in a
cathedral or church in Turin Torino then
in the 19th 20th century there have been
tests done on it on a scientific basis
about to a certain whether it's the real
deal or
not apparently they have not been able
to find any trace of of paint or pigment
on this which indicates it's not a
painting uh that's something that was
done in the 20th century then there was
radiocarbon dating done sometime in the
20th century which uh show that it it
dates back to the Middle
Ages okay so the radio carbon carbon 14
dating so I think the the Vatican gave
postage stamp sized pieces of of this uh
of this artifact to three different
Laboratories in three different
countries and all three did carbon
testing carbon uh testing on this
radiocarbon testing and they all
determin the same thing that this dates
back to sometime in the Middle
Ages so it looked like the the entire
matter was put to the rest but now
there's been a new uh experiment done on
on this on on this
fabric x-ray crystallography I think and
that's come up with whole different
story so let's take a look at this
article um where should I go for it
britanica should be a good source rather
than
Wikipedia Wikipedia o let's look at
britanica or former British colonizers
and occupiers well let's see what they
have to say about
this so blah blah blah all that
description and so on so forth ped pered
history blah blah etc etc okay analysis
of authenticity so in 2020 22
researchers in Italy published the
results of a study in which they use the
technique of wide angle x-ray scattering
to analyze a small piece of the Shroud
the study concluded that the structural
degradations of the shroud's linen were
fully compatible with those of another
linen sample that's been dated according
to historical records to 55 to 74
CE and environmental carbon
contamination was suggested as the
source of the discrepancy between those
findings and the results of the carbon
dating tests uh done in the
1980s so this new study 2022 study its
results bolstered the hypothesis that
the sh of Turin is truly from the time
of Christ although the researchers made
no conclusion regarding the Stout's
authenticity as a relic and also noted
that further testing is needed to
confirm their conclusion
so they have used a different technique
wide angle x-ray
scattering to analyze a small piece of
this this uh of this artifact the Shroud
and
the the study has concluded that the
structural degradations of the linen are
fully compatible with another L sample
that's being dated to about the first
century
ad so this is another step in the way in
in in in the Journey of understanding
this particular artifact it is not a
conclusive U finding the researchers
themselves have noted that uh further
testing is needed to to confirm the
conclusions now carbon dating is
extremely accurate but it can go wrong
if the material has been contaminated
with carbon sources or whatever from
from other types so it's known that this
shroud has been displayed over the
centuries openly in various churches and
whatnot so that could have uh introduced
some
contamination of the trout but and
yet even if some contamination is
introduced um the carbon dating results
should have been mixed not entirely
conclusive right so still looks like the
carbon dating results are to be given
more precis maybe we can do newer more
modern testing through carbon dating of
of a small piece of the sample or
something but it's it's a process it's
kind of like the Aran Invasion migration
tourism myth right new results come out
and they they seem to point in this
direction in that direction but overall
over the decades the results seem to
point in One Direction only similarly
that's the Journey of this shroud I
think it's an interesting piece of
finding I think more I agree with the
with the researchers more testing is
needed to confirm what they have
concluded theyve used a rather
unorthodox meth method wideangle x-ray
x-ray scattering which is not typically
what you use to to to date materials you
know so it's rather unorthodox and it
has to be corroborated with other me
methodologies so I think maybe they can
redo the carbon testing carbon
radiocarbon
testing U once again and see if they can
detect uh they can attribute the dating
to contamination to the Middle Ages or
something so I think uh it's too early
to draw conclusions based on this but
it's something that is definitely uh
resulted in a big tizzy of excitement in
Catholic circles and now it's it's it's
being regarded as something that's been
uh
um yeah it look so lots of people are
regarding that this that they've been
proven right they've been Vindicated and
this is the real deal I think it's a
little early for that but look it's a
question of faith and belief if you
believe in it then please feel free to
believe in it that's what I would say I
think it's it's still still too early to
make to draw any conclusions and even if
it's mined Beyond any doubt that it
dates to the first century ad even then
it doesn't prove that it is the actual
cloth that was used to wrap the body of
uh M of of Jesus Christ right it doesn't
prove
that but so that that's why I say that
at the end of the day it's a question of
faith if you believe then you believe
that's
it okay Imran Nai
says um why do Hindi Udu these two which
are the same language essentially why do
Hindi uru have Afghanistan's Persian
words Dari words and pronunciations but
not Iranian Persian words about about
98% of the Persian words that Indian
people use are from the afan dialect but
the Iranians don't use and don't know
the meanings of those words didn't
Persians and Iranians come to
India that's an interesting question and
I wonder why such questions have never
been addressed by Indian historians and
sociologists Ling linguists interesting
questions
good questions so I am not familiar with
the two dialects of Persian I don't
speak Persian I understand a bit a few
words here and there obviously like
everyone does in India but I don't I'm
not really uh that familiar with the two
versions of Persian the afan version and
the persan version if you speak if you
have an afan version spoken and a persan
version spoken I probably won't be able
to take to to tell the difference
probably uh so so that's where I'm
coming from but now assuming what Imran
is saying is absolutely correct that
Hindi Udu has afan person words not
persan person Iranian person words the
pronunciations and the words are from
the Afghan version of Persian that's
interesting if that's true it's very
interesting 98% of the Persian words are
from the afan
dialect why is that so how would one
explain that assuming that is true we
know that the turkey invasions let's go
to the
map uh we know that India was invaded by
the
Turks uh starting about um roughly let's
say a thousand years ago the Gores gnav
and so on so
forth and many and these invasions came
through the
Northwest and the first part of India
that fell to the invasions was gandhar
which is currently Afghanistan currently
in present day in the present day it's a
separate nation historically it was part
of India gandhar so the first part of
India that truly fell to the Turk
invasions and got its demographics and
uh everything else religious
demographics ethnic demographics and so
on so forth altered permanently is
Afghanistan present day Afghanistan
historical gandhar and from there from
this region the invasions wave after
wave of invasion proceeded eastwards
into
what you could call present day India
present day India
Pakistan so it makes sense that many of
the words that many of the linguistic
terms that came into India would have
come through this region and obviously
it's not like these Invaders
simply walked through Afghanistan they
would have stayed and lived there for
decades and centuries before they were
able to make inroads into the the other
parts of India and Pakistan so they
would have become
linguistically uh attuned to the
Afghanistan way of speaking dialect Etc
and maybe that's how some of these words
came into India that's one explanation
that I could offer um and we know
that when it comes to the the Turco
mugal Empire the so-called mugal Empire
which ruled India for about two two and
a half centuries uh starting from the
time of uh humayun
uh a number of Persian uh officials took
up residence in the mugul court in
Delhi so the language of the Court was
Persian and we talking about persan
Iranian persan not Afghan
persan but that never really made its
way into the common paros in India so
the language of the Court was the
Iranian person but the language of the
camp was U
the word u is probably a Mongol world
word which means Camp so the word so the
language of the camp of the military
Camp of the soldiers who were occupying
India tur soldiers who were occupying
India that language was a mongr language
mixed you you had the basic
Sanskrit vocabulary that was the the the
main structure on top of that on top of
that came various local words also
turkic words and Persian words and
probably these portion words came into
India via gandhar V Afghanistan and
maybe that's why that's the that's the
person par that we still use in Hindi
Udu I think that's the explanation I
would give and I really wonder why no
historian or sociologist has bothered to
to to to explore this issue this
question I wonder why we have linguist
Linguistics sociology and his history
departments in the country when these
interesting questions are not
addressed so I'm really glad and I'm
thankful to Imran for asking this
question and that's the kind of answer I
would venture that's the kind of theory
I would venture but one would need to to
S to to base that on more data I don't
have the data I saw this question today
and I was really intrigued by it which
is why I've picked it and I've attempted
to answer it and I'm pretty sure that
the answer I've given is pretty is quite
logical but it has to be backed up with
actual data evidence and all that so one
would need to make list of the common
Persian words that currently exist in
Hindi uru and and correlate them with
the corresponding synonyms in Iranian
person and afan person and then see
where the matches exactly actually are
and assuming that there are way more
matches with the Afghan Persian uh
versions then one would have to go back
in time and see which invasive forces
stayed how long in gandhar and then came
into India which would kind of correlate
and and again and and uh give substance
of the theory that out put forth that's
how one would approach this piece of
research from an academic perspective I
think it can be done somebody can do a
PhD on this actually nobody will do that
they want to do phds in cast and
oppression Dynamics and uh the evils of
Hinduism and the backwardness of India
and all that absolute rot
that's why we need to do something about
these parasitic Humanities departments
that are wasting our taxpayer money and
and and and and ruining the intellects
of our Bright Young
students anyway thank you Imran for a
wonderful question great
question okay sanjie says why does the
rotation of the earth slow down every
year that's a good question good
question question basic physics question
but how many I mean I'm glad people are
curious about this so let's take a look
at the Earth this is the earth it
rotates the sun rises in the East and
sets in the west which means it's
rotating in this direction you get it
it's rotating in this Direction that's
how the Earth rotates and what's the
speed of the Earth's rotation it's one
rotation every roughly 24 hours as we
know very well but here is the deal
see the Earth is about 4.4 4.5 billion
years old the solar system is 4.54
billion years old so when the Earth was
a newly formed Planet incandescent
glowing with lava and whatnot and with a
very alien atmosphere so that's about
four billion years ago let's say
4.5 so you you go back to that time the
initial Days of the New Earth that time
The Day the Earth day was way shorter
than it is now it may have been about 6
to 12 hours long probably around 6 7
hours long when when the Earth was newly
formed 4.5 billion years before today so
the Earth's day was much shorter and at
that time the Earth was spinning much
faster because of the initial angular
momentum that it acquired during its
formation as part of the protostellar
disc that gave rise to the sun and the
other planets and other objects in the
solar system so the Earth was spinning
much faster because of that initial
angular momentum it had acquired then
over billions of years over the next
four plus billion years the Earth's
rotation gradually slowed down and this
happened because of gravitational
interactions mainly with the moon and
the mechanism of the slowing down was
through tidal friction and this still
continues today so it is said it is
believed that the Earth Day what the
period of rotation it is increasing by
about two roughly 2 milliseconds every
Century which is very slow but it adds
up eventually over hundreds of billions
of years over billions of years so the
rotation slows down primarily because of
tidal friction caused by the
gravitational interaction between the
Earth and the moon so we know what tides
are right the sea Rises and Falls
periodically twice a day on whatever it
is right the moon's gravitational pull
on the earth creates tides in the
earth's oceans and this causes a bulge a
bulging effect in the earth's oceans but
the Earth's rotation causes this tidal
bulge to be slightly ahead of the Moon
and then the moon's gravity exerts a
force on this bulge creating a drag on
the Earth's rotation and this drag
results in a very slow gradual transfer
of rotational energy from the earth to
the moon and as as a result the rotation
of the earth slows down and also it has
the effect of having the moon slowly
drifting away from the
earth about 3 4 cm per year the Moon is
drifting away from the earth so it is
slowing down the rotation of the earth
and is also causing the drifting away of
the moon from the earth and there's
interaction with other solar system
bodies other celestial bodies The Sun
Also contributes to Tidal friction but
the effect is much weaker than that of
the Moon because the Moon is right here
it's right out here so all that also uh
contributes to the slowing down of the
Earth's rotation and then there is
internal friction within the Earth's
interior movements within the Earth's
interior tectonic movements the
movements between the mantle of the
earth the core of the earth that can
cause energy dissipation which can cause
changes in the rotational speed of the
earth then there is atmospheric
movements and oceanic movements these
all of these factors contribute to a
very small degree but over millions of
years all of these factors put together
is especially tidal friction because of
the Moon because of the Earth Moon
interaction that has collectively led to
the gradual lengthening of the Earth's
day from about six hours long to 24
hours which we see today so that's why
the Earth's rotation is slowing
down let's take another question from
the world of the Natural Sciences which
is
physics what happens if we replace the
sun with a black hole this is a good
question yes so let's first consider
replacing the
sun with a black hole of the same mass
as as the Sun
so who let's say through magic like this
I replace the sun instantaneously with a
black hole of the same mass as the Sun
so right where the sun is we we put a
black hole there and the sun disappears
so what
happens so first of all we sitting here
on the planet Earth will not know about
this for 8 minutes after after you
replace the sun with the black hole over
here on Earth we will not know about it
for 8 minutes because that's how long it
takes for the light of the Sun to reach
the Earth it's only after 8 minutes that
the sun will go dark so that's the first
effect the Sun Goes
dark so the light disappears so we
suddenly are in darkness wherever we are
on the planet usually half the planet is
dark and half the planet is in sunlight
right but suddenly everything goes dark
then what happens is that because of the
lack of solar radiation the heat that
comes from the
sun the Earth starts cooling very
rapidly very rapidly and within days or
weeks probably about a week or so
probably less than a week the Earth
freezes all the oceans freeze everything
freeze and that's the end of life on the
earth everybody dies All Humans all
animals everyone dies of whatever little
heat is is is left available for life on
Earth is is is in geothermal Vents and
all that deep under the oceans so those
animals that that uh thrive on
geothermal energy May survive everyone
else dies photosynthesis seizes because
of the lack of light so then all plants
die and all animals die and this
freezing everywhere and all that there
is that then because the sun no longer
exists the solar wind that is emitted by
the sun suddenly disappears because of
which the heliosphere this big bubble of
solar radiation that disappears around
the solar system and that's how and
because of this the interstellar medium
of outer space outside of the solar
system is able to now penetrate the
solar system region so that's a big
change that happens uh apart from that
nothing else
changes because the black hole that we
have replaced the sun withd has the same
mass the orbits of the planets don't
change everything continues the same way
but the the big daddy the source of heat
disappears and all everything else
changes as a consequence but what if we
replace the sun with a black hole that's
10 times the mass of the Sun a different
Mass 10 times the mass or 100 times the
mass what happens in that case all the
changes that I told you will already
happen but the planets and all the
objects in the solar system will now
feel a much stronger gravitational
attraction
to this
object at the center of the solar system
so the orbits will shrink they'll become
much tighter and the orbital velocities
will become much faster and the orbits
will become more
elliptical that's a change that will
happen and this will cause perturbations
in the orbits of and it it could cause
certain planets to be ejected out of the
solar system it could cause planetary
collisions between let's say the Earth
and Venus or than Mars or something like
that that could happen so it will cause
significant chaos in the solar system so
this is called a thought experiment
aanin experiment and it's interesting to
see interesting to do such experiments
to
see to from from a students's
perspective it's interesting to to do it
to see how much of a grasp we have on
the laws of physics so it will never
happen obviously thank God thank the
gods but yes these are the things that
that could happen that that will happen
if the sun gets replaced by a black
hole rudrajit sarar says China has faced
so many Civil Wars throughout its
history did India face such crisis in
the past if yes then why and when did it
happen if no then why did China have to
face so many Civil Wars but India did
not I don't think India has faced Civil
Wars there was a threatened Civil War in
1946 Direct action day which was WR by
jna that if you want give me the
partition of India and Pakistan then I
will give you a civil war it never
happened uh but in India's history we've
never had Civil Wars as far as I know
we've had the occupation of India by
extremely evil foreign forces the Turks
and the Europeans and they perpetrated
all kinds of atrocities on India
genocides but we didn't have Civil War
what is civil war Civil War is the
people fighting people or people
fighting the
government so it's it's chaos all around
we've never had that in India never
we've had Wars between kingdoms and all
that but civilians were never involved
but what about China China if you if you
look at the history of the past roughly
2,000 years you I'm sure you can find at
least 20 incidents 20 incidences of
Civil War which is roughly one Civil War
every Century which is staggering
actually and some of these Civil Wars
have had death TOS that are astonish L
staggering for example the typing
Rebellion that happened in the 19th
century had a death toll of 20 30
million people in just about 105
years then you you had the unan
rebellion in the 8th Century which had a
death toall about about 30 million uh
and and so many other the Dungan Revolt
that happened again in the 19th
century which was between the Chinese
and the Hui people the Muslims of East
turkistan
that had a death toll of about I don't
know at least 10
million in the Chinese Civil War um from
the 1920s to to about 19 1949 1950 that
had a death toll of of at least 10
million so you have these repeated
Cycles in China the Imperial cycles that
always end with a civil war roughly one
Civil War every century and the death
toll is typically h
astonishing crazy and you have famines
that usually accompany these Civil Wars
and and in some of these Civil Wars you
had instances of widespread cannibalism
in
China so China has had this pattern
historical pattern Civil Wars roughly
won every century and complete chaos in
the country in the kingdom in the Empire
whatever you want to call it but India
has never had that why is that so right
is is a very good question
so it's to do with culture it's to do
with geography it's to do with uh so
many things like that culture geography
so
uh there is something called the
northern China
plane so let let's Google nor the
northern China North China plane shall
we uh where okay not the map we will we
will Google the North China plane
here we are North China
plane so this is a region let's go to
the images of
that so it is this part of China that
you see highlighted in
Orange that is historically the
heartland of China the current day
nation of China it encompasses territory
territories that have historically never
been
Chinese but let's not discuss that right
now this highlighted region is the
northern China plane nor China plane and
a couple of rivers are the Bedrock of
Chinese
civilization just a few Rivers the the
Yellow River the Mong
Etc the Hang ho the Mong and couple of
two three rivers are the are the rivers
that have sustained Chinese civilization
the past roughly 2,000 3,000 years so
now we go to the
map so this western part of China has
been the heartland of China and that's
where Chinese empires have already
always is taken root in this
region India on the other hand is very
different India is a river valley
civilization there are rivers that Mark
crisscross the length and the breadth of
the Indian
subcontinent all all the way across the
subcontinent starting from from gandhar
Afghanistan all the way to wherever you
look in the subcontinent India is a
river Violet civilization China is
not then China has historically had one
language one culture and one
ethnicity not the whole of China as we
see today but historically that that
part of China the North China plane that
I showed you that historically has had
one culture one language one ethnicity
that is the Han culture the Han Chinese
language and so on and that's where
you've always had the emergence of
Kingdoms or Empires now in China there's
always been this concept so this so the
Chinese
civilization begins roughly around the
3rd Century BC with the Chin
Dynasty and youve had major Dynasty like
the Chin Dynasty the Han Dynasty the
Tang Dynasty the Ming Dynasty the Yuan
which is a conquest Dynasty sh chingis
Khan and on that's all you have these
dynasties and the Chinese have always
had this this concept called the Mandate
of Heaven what's the Mandate of Heaven
it's the idea that there can only be be
one legitimate ruler of China at any
given point in time and China obviously
is is like all culture civilizations it
its boundaries have risen and Fallen the
bounds change over time always so the
Mandate of Heaven is this idea that
there can only be one legitimate ruler
of China at any given point in time
that's the Mandate of Heaven and this
concept this idea suggests that a
Dynasty's rule is sanctioned by the gods
by Divine approval and this Mandate of
the Gods can be lost if the dynasty
fails to govern effectively and in that
case if the Mandate of Heaven Is Lost
then it is a duty of the people to rebel
against the Dynasty and throw it
down and that what is what gives rise to
the Imperial Cycles the rise of Dynasty
and
Empire which kind of consolidates that
region and the rule within it and it
because it does well initially it has
the Mandate of Heaven and it ascends to
Glory glory and eventually like every
Dynasty every Empire it starts doing
poorly it loses the Mandate of Heaven
and then there's a period of of disaster
of chaos of Civil War which can last a
decade it can last a century and then a
new Dynasty comes and a new Imperial
cycle starts that has been the pattern
of Chinese
history now in Chinese history the the
culture has been the the confusion toist
culture confusion culture which is a
legalistic culture it's all about
obeying the the authorities and all that
uh as opposed to the dhic culture that
we have in India so in China 2,000 years
we've had Buddhism roughly but the
Emperors have never followed Buddhism
they always always been
confucians uh and that's the kind of
thing it is so it's a cultural
difference and also the Mandate of
Heaven thing and that's why China has
had these horrific Civil Wars over and
over and over again in India India
also uh has at times
being unified under one Dynasty one
Empire we have so many examples the
Moran Empire the Gupta Empire the kusan
Empire the Kota Empire the Chola Empire
the marata Empire so many I can name so
many
more but India is fundamentally very
different from China in what ways is
India fundamentally different from China
we are not a monoculture like China is
today the nation of China is so large
they've taken so many territories from
other peoples that it's a multiethnic
nation but historically the Chinese were
the Han people a monoculture one
language one ethnicity one
culture in
India Hinduism the ism that we attribute
to the Hindus that itself is so
incredibly
diverse there are so many philosophical
schools of thought there are so many
customs and and traditions that have
been Incorporated and absorbed into
Hinduism it's so diverse and it's
completely
decentralized and there are so many
languages hundreds of languages and
thousands of dialects in
India so because of this incredible
diversity India genetically is the most
diverse part of the planet apart from
Africa and yet it is genetically uniform
it's a very strange conundrum so because
of this
diversity and because of having this
this plentiful abundance of water river
valleys and all that we have between the
times when India was unified under one
Empire we've had so many periods when
where India was fragmented into all
these little kingdoms sometimes big
kingdoms sometimes sometimes little
kingdoms and in India the culture is the
dharmic culture which is at its
fundamental level a culture that that uh
prioritizes nonviolence avoidable
violence of course if violence is
required we've resorted to violence like
Lord Krishna said destroy non to to
achieve the achieved nonviolence you to
destroy the violent right that way but
the Indian way of warfare was very
different when kingdoms went to war they
never touched the civilians and so on we
know the thing that's why we have never
had Civil Wars because of all these
factors which are very different from
the Chinese par the Chinese context
that's why India has never had civil
wars in which civilians get involved
almost I can't think of any time
period probably one no that's not a
Civil War right that's the first war of
independence 1857 that that was not a
civil war it was a the subcontinent wise
wide Uprising against the British
occupiers which failed at the time but
yeah that's how it went so these are the
reasons why India and China have had
such
different trajectories historical
trajectories China has these Imperial
cycles and Civil War after Civil War
India has never had that this is another
question that historians have never
bothered to take up you can write a PhD
on this topic too a comparative study of
the historical Evolution and trajectory
of of Indian and Chinese civilizations
with a focus on on the Civil War and the
dynastic cycle and Imperial cycle and
the lack of it in India such an
interesting topic nobody bothers to do
that what can I
say okay abishek Shasta says why Bengal
tiger and why not Indian tiger I'll tell
you why because the British first first
colonized Bengal in India let's go to
the
map see you have Bengal the West Bengal
region that's the first part of India
that the British colonized and the
animal the most the the scariest animal
they saw there was naturally the tiger
so they called it the Bengal tiger
because they were in Bengal and from
their perspective everything was Bengal
so the British started this terminology
and we have
slavishly idiotically basically
moronically continued that now let's so
maybe this will offend some people from
Bengal who will say why are you trying
to take away our our national our our
our our state animal or whatever yeah
let's let's go to let's go to Google and
let's see the distribution of tiger
territory in India okay so I will say
Indian tiger it will give me Bengal
tiger I can predict that already Indian
tiger it will say Bengal tiger there you
have it it will say Bengal tiger I
predicted that before it happened now
let's go inside the Wikipedia article uh
statutory warning Wikipedia is not
necessarily a reliable uh source of
information especially for Indian
history we just going through it for the
sake of saving time here is the range of
the Bengal tiger in
red all across Northern India Nepal
Himachal Pradesh Etc Bhutan the Far
Eastern regions of India arunachal
Pradesh Etc Central India lots of places
Western India lots of places and so on
and what about the region of Bal Bal
which is Bangladesh in in in West Bengal
very little so why is this the Bengal
tiger it should be the Indian tiger
naturally it's it's historically been
found all across India not just in
Bengal the British called it the Bengal
tiger because they had landed in Bengal
and they saw it there but they were not
aware that it's all across India they
came to know later but they
continued calling it the Bengal tiger
and after 1947 our wonderful
intellectuals
slavishly have continued calling it the
Bengal tiger it is the Indian
tiger it should be called the Indian
tiger I have nothing against Bengal but
look at the distribution of the Tiger in
Bengal hardly a handful it's the Indian
tiger and the Bengal variant is not some
subspecies of the Indian tiger it is
just the Indian tiger so it should be
the Indian Tiger but we are so deeply
mentally colonized that these simple
things also we don't notice so I would
like to thank abishek shirasa for
pointing this out it is the Indian tiger
not the Bengal
tiger okay okay Minal says how can we
improve the the state of Agriculture the
condition of agriculture in bhat and
make bhat an export Hub as we are good
with agriculture but we don't Excel
there and how do we educate our
Farmers so if I recall correctly more
than half of the India of India's of
bat's population is is engaged in
agriculture and agriculture Allied
activities I think close to 55% of our
population is engaged in either
agriculture or things related to
agriculture but the contribution of
Agriculture to India's GDP is less than
20% maybe 18 19% if my memory serves me
right why is it so so what can we do
about this first of all we have to
understand that this entire situation
the root cause of that is the British uh
the
British uh practice of of of the the the
rathari system that they had instituted
in India which stole the land from
Indians and placed it in the hands of
zamindars they they continued the mul
practice and and took it took it
nationwide so people who you know today
um most Indians don't own land most
Indians don't own
land historically everybody had land the
British stole the land of the Indians
put it in the hands of the government
and the zamindars and then forced
Indians to do subsistence farming on
those small Parcels of land that they
they were would be
allotted and that's how they ruined
India so today you have people who are
engaged in agriculture more than half
this the population but it's very
inefficient and it it it contributes
less than 20% of the of the nation's GDP
what should be
done I'll tell you something if you give
most Indians engaged in agriculture a
chance they will move away from
agriculture they would like to to do
something
else because historically most Indians
were not engaged in agriculture India
was the world's first fully
industrialized civilization we had our
own Industries and people had all these
occupations and and whatever whatever
trades that they specialized in all that
was destroyed and people were forced
into subsistence farming by the British
that's how they de-industrialized India
so if you give most people a chance they
will move away from agriculture so what
needs to happen is this we need to
mechanize the agriculture we need to
bring the agricultural practices in the
24th century if you look at the biggest
agricultural exporters in the world
let's say the biggest agricultural
exporters of wheat would probably the
wheat would probably be the us or Russia
or Ukraine used to be the one right they
have industrial agriculture so maybe two
three % of the population is engaged in
agriculture but they have access to the
modern equipment the big machines and
all that which are incredibly efficient
so in these developed countries maybe
two three four 5% of the population is
engaged in agriculture but they
contribute way more of the
GDP so that's what we need in India for
that we will need to have a booming
economy we will need to have sufficient
job production so that people can be
brought out of
agriculture and then we can have
agriculture becoming more efficient with
the use of industrial and methods and
and better machines and all that so
that's the kind of thing we need in
India you can't have 55% of of your
population doing agriculture with very
little return it's bad for everyone so
we do need to get better at agriculture
we we we are reasonably self-sufficient
in most things we import pulses Etc from
various countries Africa and so on
but overall we we're pretty we're in a
good spot but I'm sure we can do better
than what we are doing right now so we
need to get more people actually out of
Agriculture give them actual good
prospects in various Industries and all
that and the ones who remain in
agriculture they should be able to do it
way more efficiently than what is being
done right
now
shubam Vare says how to bring Civic
sense in Indians
it's very easy implement the
arastra I'm serious the AR shastra is
not just about economics it's about
governance it's about how to govern an
Empire and it prescribes various kinds
of punishments and so on so forth for
various offenses it prescribes how
government officials should comport
themselves and so
on what needs to happen it's it's very
simple simple Civic sense means a lack
of Civic sense means lack of Standards
lack of Behavioral standards lack of
good habits and all spitting on the road
littering everywhere and so on let's
talk about littering let's talk about
the fact that in many Indian towns and
cities you have garbage on the streets
why is it
so first of all because there is no
punishment for littering and dumping
stuff where wherever you want you eating
a pack of of of of junk food chips you
you done you just dump it wherever it is
and move on that's typically what it do
right um there is no fine there's no
punishment for it you make it such that
if somebody does such a thing punishment
is guaranteed in a timely manner then
people will stop doing
it
then that's one example spitting is
another example look at what Singapore
did they implemented harsh fines for all
these offenses and they made it a
certainty that if you do that if you
break the law you're going to be
punished
guarantee in in a certain amount of time
so people stopped doing that because it
was painful that's all you have to do
that's all you have to do it's not a
defect of Indian Society it's a defect
of Indian governance that there are
there are no punishments for these for
these behaviors and that's how people
slowly their their standards decline the
standards drop that's all it is you have
to ensure that punishment is guaranteed
it doesn't have to be really harsh
punishments but it should
be
um um it doesn't need to be
harsh but it should the punishments
should be inconveniences to the people
who are being punished you have to go
and appear in court and spend one day
there you lose one day it's
inconvenience more than a punishment and
you to pay a fine let's say a th000
rupees but you have to turn up at the
court and so and so time wait in line
and then you wait your turn and come in
front of the judge listen to a dressing
down and and scolding and then your name
is displayed somewhere for doing
something and then you pay the fine that
sort of thing you you waste a day it's
an inconvenience and you never want to
have have that again right so guarantee
the S of punishment then everybody will
behave why do Indians behave so well
outside the
country why are Indians the most low
abiding people outside the country
because in those
countries uh punishment for such things
is guaranteed almost guaranteed and
Indians naturally are low abiding people
that's how we do it it's a failure of
the governance system that you don't
have Civic sense in
Indians um
okay Frey bunel says I live in Dublin
Ireland and I see that no one here
Dublin Dublin is it
Ireland or is it
Scotland it's the capital of the
Republic of Ireland Scotland is
Edinburgh okay so uh Shan lives in
Dublin he sees and I see that no one
here speaks GIC or Irish school students
even joke that they would rather learn
German or Spanish as it would be more
useful in the job market so I often
wonder wonder how do languages die can
the same happen to our Indian languages
as these days we see more and more
people speaking English proudly but most
words in a sentence are English and only
a few are in Hindi is this normal also
countries like Ireland Ireland have
extremely small armies they have about
7,500
soldiers good point how do they survive
and does depending on the US and the EU
take away their sovereignty let me
answer the second part of the question
question first if a nation has 7,500
soldiers that nation is
colonized okay it's not a Sovereign
Nation so yes Ireland Scot sovereignty
has been taken over by the UK by the US
EU yeah of course yeah Ireland hasn't
done brexit right Northern Ireland is
under British occupation that which has
suffered brexit but Ireland hasn't so
Ireland is a member of the EU probably
NATO as well if I'm not mistaken and
then that's where all the sovereignty
disappears so Ireland is not a Sovereign
Nation if you have 7,500 soldiers
under is Ireland a member of NATO let me
see Ireland NATO I'm just quickly
Googling okay Ireland is not a member of
NATO but good for it but well makes no
real difference you're part of the
anglosphere despite not being an English
speaking Nation sad so coming to the
main part of the question no one speaks
GIC or Irish in Ireland and students
joke they would learn a foreign language
rather than their own language because
it's more useful the job market it's
very similar to what's happening in
India like you point out rightfully most
Indians speak Hindi speaking people
speak English a combination of English
and Hindi and that's how languages die
when you when you no longer value your
language and it's not it's the
government has to step in and Ensure
that the education system is based in
Indian languages in the mother tongues
of students and secondly that the job
market does not require you to know
English should make it illegal should
make it a punishable offense for uh for
a company to to to require that you
speak good English to get a
job so these things have to be
implemented that's called decolonization
and we are not doing that and that's why
it's it's killing our languages where is
the literature in in local Indian
languages hardly a few publication
ations most Regional language public
Publications Publishers have
disappeared in if it continues this way
in a century you will have hardly any
Indian culture left most Indian
languages will be dead that's what will
happen this is how languages die you can
actually map the process of the of the
of the ongoing death of a
language uh so yeah it's it's it's
happening to our Indian languages and in
in many Indian languages will die out in
the next few decades if nothing is
changed and right now nothing is being
done to change it so that's where I am
very disappointed with the Modi
government what have they done to
strengthen India's culture and languages
tell me the top five
initiatives the government has taken in
the field of culture and and
civilization and language
nothing it's very disappointing and yeah
that's all I can say about this
swastika says is arranged marriage a bad
thing it's looked down upon in the west
it's considered to be embarrassing but
it's a millennia old tradition and
apparently considered one of the reasons
for lower than average divorce rate in
India and I believe it's helpful for
those who don't like to date and see
dating as a burden but will this
tradition disappear as Indians are wnab
be Americans though I've read that even
many Americans complain about how hard
the dating scene has become uh nothing
wrong with love marriage but it's
helpful to have options in a society as
not every individual is the same is
arranged marriage a bad thing no it's
not a bad thing it's been the practice
not just in India but other parts of the
world also for thousands of years King
Richard the first of England Richard Kon
Richard the
lionard he arranged his
marriage with with bingara of Spain her
father's name was Sancho if I if I
remember
um Richard I first he arranged his
sister's marriage to I forget who
too he he tried to arrange his sister's
marriage sister Joanna's marriage to the
son of Salah
Saladin and there are so many examples
of AR marriages in the
west and in in in non-aristocratic
society also marriages would be arranged
so it's always been there it's only in
recent times that the West has approved
its own traditions and now they claim
that whatever they're doing right now at
the present moment is the right thing
and we being the mentally
colonized society that we are saddled
with this deep inferiority complex we
have to copy and ape slavishly ape
everything the West
does look I am not saying that everybody
should have an arranged marriage you can
have a love marriage too why not nothing
wrong with it but why do you have to uh
look down upon arranged
marriages and you are right I think one
of the reasons why uh the average
divorce rate is so low in India is
because of arranged
marriages uh so I have nothing against
love marriages I have nothing against
arranged marriages either it's a
tradition that we've had it's a custom
we've had it's been part of our culture
civilization and why do we have to kill
that um at the end of the day in life
you know what really matters is that you
have a stable marriage and and peace
between between the two partners and
very often in these love marriages
unless you're lucky it it it very often
goes bad because there's so many factors
that go into a stable marriage there
there has to be compa compatibility not
just between the two individuals but
between the families the the family
cultures should match and the values and
standards should match and so much needs
to match and often it's it's issues
beyond the two individuals who are
married that that caused the rift and
arranged marriages prevent all that but
yeah we we are a deeply deeply mentally
colonized Society we have to we are the
process of of of of dismantling
everything that we have had for
thousands of years and just blindly
aping the West the West is going to
collapse Western Society is going to
collapse in a few years and decades it's
it's the process is is be is beginning
it's already begun it's it's in it's in
process we want to jump on Into the
Fire it's so um
unfortunate and and how do we comat
combat that by by teaching our culture
to our kids by reforming the education
system but the government won't do that
the government won't do
that okay rodit sarar says why is
Central and South America insignificant
so insignificant in World
politics ah good question let's go to
the map Central South America Central
America starts with Mexico Mexico then
we have Guatemala Nicaragua Costa and
Panama and of course you have Biz
Honduras El
Salvador and then you have South America
which is Colombia Venezuela Ecuador and
all the other nations the biggest ones
are obviously Brazil and Argentina and
you have a wonderful Chile as well and
all of these nations are geopolitically
insignificant Brazil is a member of but
Brazil is Brazil so if you go back in
history you will see that the Americans
had something called the Monro Doctrine
all these nations in South America they
used to be European colonies all were
European colonies Europeans had divided
up the land among themselves various
European countries or kingdoms and they
were in the process of extracting
everything of value out of the place out
of these territories
then an incredible phenomenon burst up
upon the scene Napoleon B
and the Napoleonic Wars ensued and all
these European kingdoms lost control of
the territories in the Americas and
that's how these new nations
emerged then the Americans the United
States they were worried the the
Europeans will will once again try to
reassume control over these nations so
that's why they instituted the mandro
doctrine initially the British
cooperated with the Americans in
enforcing the mundro doctrine but then
the Americans became powerful in their
own right and they ensured that no other
power could influence anything in the
Americas North America Central America
South America and today if you see and
they have instituted various in various
regime change operations Etc in the
Americas the Americans p no is example
and and much more and that's how they
have uh maintained complete control over
these nations in the Americas and today
every single nation in the Americas is a
vasal of the United States and that's
why Central and South America are
insignificant in World
politics
okay so what else do we have let's I I'm
out of questions I still have more
questions but let me take some questions
from the chat now live chat for a few
minutes before I end today's session
because we have already gone past two
hours
okay um Romans woried Mitra Assyria has
a city called assur zoroastrians woried
varuna can you please explain the
connections to ancient Hinduism the
world was interconnected the ancient
world for thousands of years was
interconnected MRA vun are the the TW
are the deities that that emerged out of
Hinduism out of the Vic Pantheon and the
worship of MRA eventually reached Ro
out of India that's a
guarantee assur may or may not be
related to India the Zoro obviously
worshiped varuna which who is Uranus
uranos in the Greek Roman Pantheon
so the
ancient world as in ancient Eurasia you
had lots and lots of local distinct
local manifestations of the same culture
in the same Pantheon of Gods with
different names and that's the
connection with ancient Hinduism and of
all these cultures the oldest is the
rigc Hindu
culture
okay what else do we have
um let's go all the way down and see
what questions
uh abijit butin KGB agent what's your
view on Poland's
blinken remark they didn't exactly use
that language they told him to go to
hell or
something uh they didn't ask him to F
off they those those those
parliamentarians those MPS they told
blinkin to to get out or leave or go to
hell or something so what's happening is
the Ukraine war is is going badly
obviously for Ukraine and for the West
it's a disaster for the country of
Ukraine it's a complete disaster it's
it's tragic for the Ukraine but
eventually Ukraine will be spent and
there will be nothing left ukra for no
no more soldiers left to fight so who's
next well look at the map who's next
that's what the Americans are looking
now so if you look at the region if you
look west of Ukraine you have Poland the
Americans are trying to turn Poland into
a new European superpower military
superpower by selling it weapons and all
that and they would if if Ukraine
eventually Falls which it eventually
most likely will to the
Russians then the Americans will then
want Poland to get involved in the next
phase of the war and that's why the
Polish MPS who understand what the
Americans are doing very well they told
blinkin the Secretary of State to get
lost because he has come he apparently
has reached Poland to set the foundation
the groundwork to involve Poland in the
next phase of the
war and that will ruin Poland the same
way it's ruined Ukraine so so there you
have
it hsh says the recent news popped up
saying that India China has have agreed
on working with urgency on the Lac
disengagement I've already discussed
this in depth about an hour ago so yes
something is a foot I'm
glad
um
okay Kabir gambhir says I'm a student at
DTU attire one college they teach almost
all student all subjects pathetically
unsurprisingly with no visualization
some are good due to the professor but
if this is in DTU a top Tire College
what about Tire two or three colleges
that is the story of the Indian
education system garbage trash rotten
what can I
say and
and what's
genuinely unfortunate is that nothing is
being done to address this new education
policy 2022 or 24 whatever the number is
it is nothing it solves no real problem
it doesn't do anything it's just a
cosmetic exercise an exercise in
cosmetics so I'm sorry that you're going
through this everybody else is going
through this and I don't know what the
solution is the government isn't do
doing a thing to solve this problem
sad okay I'll take this question and end
it over here DJ Kat says why is the BCCI
not canceling the cricket series with
Bangladesh with these Pakistan in the
wake of the horrific unmitigated
atrocities against the Hindus how
spineless and C howly are
they
um yeah it's it's a I I believe the the
the East Pakistan team has reached India
to play that series I don't know how
many matches or whatever there is but
there's something I think look these
series are planned years in
advance um and I'm sure there will be
legal and other repercussions to
canceling the
CDs um so maybe that's why they're doing
they're not
canceling the series no don't bring
polit don't mix politics and Sport
apparently or something I would not go
to the extent of calling them spineless
and cowardly they have to run see the
BCCI is running a business the they're
the most powerful Cricket Board on the
planet it's an asset to have as a
nation so
um so I will I will I will not be so
harsh on the BCCI and say that they're
spinless and cowardly they just trying
to run the game in the country
understand that the BCCI is an asset for
India it's the most powerful
body in the sport of cricket and it
gives India tremendous amount of control
and and Power in in this particular
sport so it's a good thing to
have and yeah but I would actually have
preferred to have the series cancelled
in in in light of the horrors that are
being perpetrated on the on the Hindus
of Bangladesh I I totally agree so maybe
it's not for the BCCI to decide this
maybe the government of India would have
to step in if it will step in I I doubt
it will because of various uh because of
various diplomatic and other
reasons Mr Modi has been emphasizing
this repeatedly that there is the need
in Bangladesh to safeguard the lives and
and and the the interests of Hindus
there he has raised this issue at
multiple levels will he take the step of
canceling the series with East Pakistan
I'm not sure about that but I would not
let lay the owners on the BCCI if if if
a Series has to be canceled it has to be
the decision has to be taken at a higher
level so yeah it's compl it's
complicated maybe we will not do that
but I am not particularly happy to see
the Bangladesh team in India right now
the East Pakistan team so I will leave
it at
that and with that I'm going to end this
session two hours plus uh minutes 2
hours 13 minutes now so thank you so
much for all your questions
um and uh I will see you in the sessions
that we do next week so please uh keep
asking questions like I said please keep
raising your standards keep improving
yourselves keep doing the things that
are difficult but but good for you and
thank you once again for all the
questions I'll see you in the live
streams that I'll do next week so take
care